Macson Mathew

Senior Engineer Instrumentation

A competent professional with total 12.25 years of Refinery experience in Construction, Commissioning, Maintenance of field instruments and control system, automation and reliability.

Aspiring to carve a niche for myself across the horizon with an organization of reputation that would enable the application of my technical knowledge and to deliver maximum returns to the company's business and growth objectives.



WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Instrumentation Engineer (Assistant General Manager)

Reliance Industries

Jamnagar, India

10/2019 – Present Job Responsibilities

- Furnish technical inputs to maintenance group for upgrade and obsolescence issues.
- Warrant development and implementation of management of change(MoC) by participating in site engineering studies. Determine the feasibility of introducing modification to enhance system reliability and efficiency of plants
- Foster the maintenance team for effective failure analysis, bad actors identification and engage in RCA's for plant reliability improvement.
- Purvey technical inputs for expansions in existing facilities, participate in SIL studies to ensure instrumentation system deficiencies are addressed in the project stage.
- Steer the team to develop solutions for problem resolution and implement the solution in a time bound manner.
- Proffer improvements in internal processes against best practices to ensure ease of maintenance and increased reliability.
- Generate MIS, progress reports to provide accurate timely data to higher management for effectively managing the business.

Senior Instrumentation Engineer (Senior Manager)

Reliance Industries

Jamnagar, India

02/2015 - 09/2019

Job Responsibilities

- Formulate plans, review and analyze preventive maintenance strategy for analyzers in order to achieve highest efficiency of the activities for reliable and safe operation.
- Render technical advice during troubleshooting of instrument failures to find the root cause and best solution in order to restore the functionality back to normal.
- Establish new inventory/cataloguing where necessary. Update information in the inventory to ensure it is relevant for the current operation.
- Classify, study, propose and implement areas for improvement(project) to enhance the operation, improve total equipment reliability through MoC(Management of Change) procedures.
- Populate inputs into SAP to ensure data and history of maintenance activities are captured accurately thereby achieving a strong database for ease
 of maintenance in future.
- Forecast and prepare budget for instrument related activities i.e. maintenance, shutdown and project for consolidation into annual department budget. Scrutinize budget utilization closely and provide justification for variance.
- Supervise and groom subordinates to develop their technical knowledge, skills and competencies.

Field & Control System Engineer (Manager)

Reliance Industries

Jamnagar, India

09/2007 - 02/2015 Job Responsibilities

- Functioned as commissioning and maintenance engineer in JERP (Jamnagar Export Refinery Project) of Reliance Industries Limited, the largest grass root refinery of the world.
- Instrumental in preparation of detailed / micro schedules for site works, overall project schedules, procedures for site execution thereby ensuring optimum implementation time with no reworks.
- Acquainted in Installation, commissioning & trouble shooting of Rosemount ATG (Automatic Tank Gauging) system, F&G, DCS, CTM, MCMS and analyzer systems(CEMS,FTNIR,GC,O2,pH,PM,CH4..etc)
- Familiar with Ifix software of Daniel CTM, Allen-Bradley PLC (5/40 & 5/60) & Siemens S7 300, FOXBORO I/A Series 8.2.3 DCS of Invensys, Triconex ESD Tristation 1131 software & Bently-Neveda MCMS 3500 (Machine Conditioning and Monitoring System).
- Assure the continuous availability of field instruments and control systems by conducting periodic planned maintenance, LLF(Look, Listen and Feel)
 and LCI (Last Chance Inspection) rounds thereby ensuring no unplanned downtime and no production losses.
- Contribute as team member in Process Hazard Analysis (PHA) study, as part of PSSR team (PreStart up Safety Review) for identifying any flaws before startup of plants after shutdown/slowdown.

CONFERENCES & COURSES

S7 300 PLC with Step 7 Training (10/2017 – 10/2017)

Siemens

Automation India (10/2016 - 10/2016)

ISA India

Liquid Hydrocarbon flow measurement and custody transfer (04/2014 – 04/2014)

FLUID CONTROL RESEARCH INSTITUTE

Triconex - Tristation 1131 training (02/2014 – 03/2014)

Invensys

Defect Elimination/Root Cause Analysis Training (05/2013 – 05/2013)

Shell

Custody meter transfer training (05/2010 – 05/2010)

Emerson

EDUCATION

Bachelors in Electronics and Instrumentation Engineering

Federal Institute of Science & Technology

05/2003 – 07/2007 Kerala, India

LANGUAGES

English Hindi Malayalam

Native or Bilingual Proficiency Full Professional Proficiency Native or Bilingual Proficiency